Guide to the Warren Jay Vinton papers, 1932-1969
Vinton, Warren Jay papers, 1932-1969
- Series IV. First Assistant Commissioner, Public Housing Authority, file, 1949-1957. Listed Alphabetically
  - "Financing, Temporary"-Memoranda from Vinton and press releases on sale of temporary notes of local housing authorities while Vinton Assistant Commissioner (file of releases continued under heading "P.H.A. Temporary Sale.. ."), 1954-1957 (Box 19)
  - [Fitzpatrick, B.T.]-correspondence, draft of charter for corporate rental housing mortgagers, draft of insurance debenture financing bill from B.T. Fitzpatrick, former General Counsel, Housing and Home Finance Agency (to 1954), 1956-1957; 1959-1960 (Box 20)
  - "Housing for Elderly and/or Single"-Correspondence, draft of amendment of Public Housing Act, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - [Joint Committee on Non-essential Federal Expenditures]-correspondence, reports, etc. in answer to questions from Congressional Committee Chairman, Harry Byrd, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - [Management Appraisal Public Housing Administration]-Study by Cresap, McCormick and Paget, Managment Consultants, (in binder); Memorandum report in examination of financing activities (in binder); correspondence and memoranda enclosed, 1956 (Box 10)
  - [PHA Racial Policy [Public Housing Administration]- Statements, memoranda, clippings, binder on PHA policies, Aug. 18, 1949-Sept. 29, 1955 (Box 19)
  - [Public Housing Authority]-Outstanding Amount of Local Housing Authority Obligations held Private Investors; charts, 1949-1965 (Box 20)
  - [Public Housing Administration, Sale of Temporary notes and bonds]-Announcements of sale of temporary notes of Local Housing Authorities and Housing Authority bonds, 1953, 1957-1968 (Box 20)
  - [Public Housing Authority, Sales of New Housing Authority Bonds]- Charts, 1951-1965 and Ms. chart on specimen yield (Box 20)
  - [Public Housing Administration, Temporary Note Sales]-Charts on notes sales and comparision of average interest rate with average interest on Treaury Bills sold just previously, 1953-1954, 1955-1956, 1957-58, 1959-60, 1961-63, 1964-; charts of note sales 1939-1956, chart of sales and balances 1939-1956, comparison chart 1950-1952, 1939-1964 (Box 20)
  - "Quotations"-Identification of quotations; 1950-1959 [2nd file] (Box 17)
  - "Slum Sites-Limitations on Cost"-Memoranda, correspondence on costs of slum land for redevelopment, especially concerning case of Norfolk (Va.) Redevelopment and Housing Authority, report "Slum Land Acquisitions: Pattern of Payments.. ." File incl. papers pulled from pre 1949 file headed Slum Clearance Sites, 1943-[1950-1954] (Box 19)
  - "Statements, etc., For and Against Public Housing 1949, 1950, 1951"-Clippings, reports, etc. from various cities and states, Dec. 15, 1949-Oct. 24, 1951 (Box 23)
  - "Statements, etc. For and Against Public Housing 1952, 1953, 1954, 1955, 1956, 1967"-From various cities and states, clippings, reports, etc., Jan. 1952-Oct. 4, 1956 (Box 23)
  - "Statements in Response to Senator Byrd's Request of 6/18/54 7/23/54"-Statement on low-rent housing program of P.H.A., 1954 (Box 16)
  - "Statements in Response to Senator Byrd's Request of 8/3/54 9/2/54"-Statement on low-rent housing program of P.H.A., 1954 (Box 16)
  - "Statements in Response to Senator Byrd's Request of 10/15/54 1/7/55"-Statements on programs of P.H.A., 1954 (Box 16)
  - "Statements on Programs Administered by the PHA as of June 30, 1954 [Capehart] [3 1/55] "-Statement on various programs and their history, 1955 (Box 16)
  - "Tax Exemption of Local Housing Authority Bonds"-correspondence,clippings, 1954-1957 (Box 17)
  - "The Temporary Financing Program of the Public Housing Administration"-report and reprint from The Daily Bond Buyer, 1957 (Box 16)
  - "Treasury-PHA Borrowing from"-[Public Housing Administration], memoranda, correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - [Vinton Resignation]-letters, cards, speeches and programs for 3 parties honoring Vinton on his leaving of Civil Service: Bond dealers luncheon NYC Sept. 12, 1957; HHFA cocktail party Sept. 23, 1957; NAHO dinner Sept. 24, 1957, Aug. 16-Dec. 5, 1957 (Box 23)
  - [Wurster] "Bauer, Catherine"-correspondence, articles on housing policy, housing market analysis, comments; (folder tab "Bauer," Catherine Bauer married William Wurster, 1940, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
- Series V. Consultant Files, 1957-1966. Listed Alphabetically
  - [Ad Hoc Public Housing Review Committee]-Reports, recommendations, minutes (MC and MS), 1957-1960 (Box 21)
  - [Awards and Resolutions]-Letters, programs, news releases and clippings on awards given to Vinton by National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials, 1967, American Society of Planning Officials 1959-1964 and American Institute of Planners, 1964, Dec. 4, 1957-Sept. 28, 1964 (Box 23)
  - Chicago Conference on Housing, "Appendix to Working Papers by W.J.V. "Appendix to Working Papers for Chicago Conference, Feb. 26-17, 1960, "Example of a Comprehensive Program," (MC) 2 copies; Feb. 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Comments on W.J.V. Draft of Interim Report:" Correspondence, May 3-Dec. 6, 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Data for Working Paper" [for Chicago Metro. Housing and Planning Council]: Date arranged by chapters, Nov. 30, 1959-April 8, 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Correspondence [sic], Speeches and Releases:"Material on paper prepared by W.J.V. for Conference on Housing the Economically and Socially Disadvantaged Groups in the Population, held by Metropolitan housing and Planning Council of Chicago; 1969 outline of schedule for production of report, Nov. 6, 1959-March 23, 1961; June 7, 1969 (Box 15)
    - "Drafts and notes-unused:" Material for Chicago Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council meeting and report, Feb. 27, 1960 (Box 15)
    - Draft of Interim Report by W.J.V:" Report of the Conference on Housing and the Economically and Socially Disadvantaged Groups in the Population, Chicago, February 26-27, 1960, 3 copies, 1 annotated to show differences between Vinton's and published report, 2 copies unused 5 pp. draft MC, June 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Interim Report:" Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council 1) Interim Report on Housing the Economically and Socially Disadvantaged Groups in the Population. Proceedings and working papers of Conference.. .Feb. 26-27, 1960 3 cop., 2 with report by Vinton (incomplete) and by Ernest Fisher, 3rd copy with no reports (MC) New York Times clipping (PC); 2) Recommendations.. .Jan. 1961, Chicago, 3 copies, June 1960-Jan. 1961 (Box 15)
    - "Preliminary Outline of Working Paper:" 4 copies, MC for Chicago Conference on Housing for low income families of Chicago Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council, Dec. 4, 1959 (Box 15)
    - "Record of Sessions Feb. 26-27, 1960:" Autograph notes on Conference on Housing the Economically and Socially Disadvantaged Groups in the Population sponsorred by Chicago Metropolitan Housing and Planning Conference at Moraine Hotel, Highland Park, Ill. (Box 15)
    - "Revised Outline of Working Paper:" 4 copies, MC for Chicago Conference on Housing for low income families of Chicago Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council, Jan. 12, 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Working Paper by W.J.V.:" 4 copies, 1 appendix, MC 3 editions for Conference on Housing the Economically and Socially Disadvantaged Groups in the Population sponsored by Chicago Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council, Feb. 12-27, 1960 (Box 15)
    - [Democratic Party and Urban Problems]-Mayors for Kennedy-Johnson newsletter, 1960 Democratic platform, Democratic National Committee fact sheet and pamphlet #4 in series "State of Our Cities and Suburbs in a Changing America," invitation from J.F. Kennedy to Pittsburgh Conference on urban problems, Sept. 14, 1960 (Box 1)
  - [National Association of Home Builders]-Report "10 Point Program for 1965" in folder (Box 20)
  - [National Capital Housing Authority]-correspondence and reports on public housing sites and urban renewal, enclosing also Management Survey of National Capital Housing Authority by Public Housing Administration, MS notes of meeting, 1957-1959 (Box 20)
  - National Housing Conference
    - [National Housing Conference Housing Yearbook-1961]: Draft of text and Ms calculations for article "The Housing Census of 1960 or the Triumph of Suburbia" for 1961 yearbook (Box 24)
    - "National Housing Conference-Housing Yearbook-1964:" correspondence, reports, tables, drafts, housing yearbook, clipping for statistical section by Vinton from Lee F. Johnson, 1963-1964 (Box 24)
    - "National Housing Conference-Housing Yearbook-1965:" Correspondence, reports, PC, MC, Housing yearbook, draft, proofs for statistical section (Box 24)
    - "National Housing Conference-Housing Yearbook-1966:" Housing Yearbook, reports, rough drafts, PC, MC, for statistical section (Box 24)
    - "National Housing Conference-Housing Yearbook-1967:" Reports, articles, rough drafts, tables, correspondence for statistical section, 1964-1967 (Box 24)
  - [Public Housing Administration Bond Sales]-Housing and Home Finance Agency, Public Housing Administration; clipped notices, especially an issue and sale of PHA notes and bonds, 1958-1962 (Box 20)
  - [Views on Public Housing]-Symposium of letters written at the request of Norman P. Mason, U.S. Housing Administrator; publication and correspondence with Vinton from Mason and National Public Housing Conference on subjects, 1959-1960 (Box 13)
  - [Vinton Banquet]-letters, invitations, clipping concerning testimonial dinner given Mr. and Mrs. Vinton Aug. 5, 1969, July 30-Aug. 6, 1969 (Box 23)
  - [Vinton Lectureship]-letters, announcements, broadside, clipping on establishment of and first lecture in Vinton Lectureship in Planning at Montgomery College under the sponsorship of Montgomery County Citizen's Planning Assoc., July 21-Dec. 21, 1969 (Box 23)
  - [Wurster] "Bauer, Catherine"-Correspondence, paper from seminar Metropolitan Housing Market Needs Analysis, papers on physical environment and renewal, memoriam on death of Catherine Bauer, Nov. 1964; Catherine Bauer married William Wurster in 1940, 1957-1964 (Box 4)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence, especially concerning Vinton's speeches at American Society of Planning Officials and National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials, Vintons criticism on N.H.C. proposed release Low Cost Housing, bibliography, 1958 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence personal and concerning Vinton's speeches and articles, memoranda MS notes and statements on use of residual receipts from Local Housing Authorities, clipped MS notes on "Methods for Authorizing Expenditures Beyond Current Year", 1959 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence, draft, esp. concerning anticipated changes by new administration, 1960 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence on Unmet Needs legislative requirements, article Vinton didn't complete for Encyclopedia Britannica, Presidential message, letters of thanks for congratulations from Robt. Weaver, Sen. Sparkman, etc., 1961 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Clipped papers on 25th anniversary of Public Housing Administration anniversary luncheon, 1962 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence from New York State on low-rent housing, clip of papers on Urban Renewal Commission's campaign to improve urban renewal design, 1963 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence from Mel Scott on his Greenbelt research, from Albert Mayer on AIP on Housing Act, 1965 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence from Albert Mayer on history of Greenbelt towns, 1966 (Box 20)
  - [Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chronological)]-Correspondence from Walter Blucher and Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning, 1969 (Box 20)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports-Chronologically Arranged, 1935-1969
  - Miscellaneous Reports and Correspondence: Temporary Emergency Relief Administration, Division of Rural Activities. Subsistance Garden Activities, 1935 TS; General Summary of Urbanism Report on Urban Land Policies in Nov. 1936 TS; 3rd National Conference on Labor Legislation, Report of Committee on Housing Nov. 9, 1936, TS; U.S. Dept. of Labor, Housing for Workers, 2 drafts by Warren Jay Vinton 7/10/36 TS; Memorandum to J.S. Lansill, Land Program of Federal Emergency Relief Administration by Bushrod Allen on Study of Population Redistribution, April 1935 TS; copy of letter from Comptroller General to Federal Emergency Administrator of Public Works on financial responsibility of federal government to federal project housing, Jan. 17, 1936, TS, list of planners, c. 1936; 1935-1936 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Misc. corres., notes, memoranda, etc., esp. inter-office memoranda from Nathan Straus on setting up office and administrative procedure for limited States Housing Authority, including La Guardia telegram, outline and drafts on policy and procedures; from Nathan Struas, Charles Abrams, Jacob Crane, 1937 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Misc. corres., memoranda, reports, etc., esp. facilitative memoranda from Nathan Strauss, USHA administrator, and notes on tour of Capt. R.L. Reiss, 1938 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres., memoranda dealing with planning and policy making functions of USHA, setting of rent policy making functions of USHA, drafts of report on War Developments and Housing by Warren Jay Vinton and Boris Skislokin; timetable for approval of loan contracts; memoranda on housing by Capt. Reiss, Feb. 21, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Misc. corres., reports, charts, memoranda on USHA: comparision with European housing projects, costs of defense housing, tenant selection; minutes of New York meeting with NAHO committee, 1940 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres. and memoranda concerning data on post war emergency, comments on statements by C.F. Palmer, Defense Housing Coordinator, staffing of USHA, discussion of low-rent housing need with Edith Elmer Wood, correspondence from Miles Coban on Housing Survey of Twentieth Century Fund, memorandum on new procedure for processing USHA projects, 1941 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Draft on "Factors and Procedures in Determining Need and in Selection Sites for Low-Cost Housing" by Russell Black and Raymond Snow, letter to B.J. Hovde on relations between FPHA central and regional offices and local housing authorities copy of letter transferring powers of Defense Housing Coordination to NH Agency, 1942 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Report by Division of Research and Statistics on "Dwelling Unit Costs of Publicly and Priately Financed Rental Housing Projects in the United States," report on funds and legislation required by postwar housing, memorandum from Coleman Woodbury on NHA contacts with local authorities, 1943 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Memoranda on land costs, objectives for legislation and new plans for financing, report "Suggested Systems of Limitation of Maximum FPHA Annual Contributions in Relation ot Economic Rent," TS copy "Administrative History of Defense Homes Corporation" by H.E. Cahen, 1944 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Memoranda from Philip Klutznick and Charles Ascher on preparation of testimony for housing legislation, and outline of testimony; revised and checked draft of "Suggested Procedures for Development and Managment of FPHA aided projects; letter for Elizabeth Wood, Chicago Housing Authority, list and notes of exhibited submitted to Civil Service Commission [re classification WJV's job] chart on income of urban families, 1945 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Correspondence from National Association Housing Officials, National Home and Property Owners Foundation, Secretary of Treasury on FPHA financing, Bureau of the Budget on statistical standards, memoranda, charts on project costs, announcements of resignation of P. Klutznick and appointment of Dillon Myer as Commissioner, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Biographical note on F.J. Osborn [British New Towns Expert], memoranda on permanent financing, and on insurance coverage of project letter from E.J.Bahn, map on plan of town in Cook and Will Counties and tracing, chart "How the Low-Rent Housing Program Works," memoranda on limitations of public housing program, 1947 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Memorandum, statement on payment in lieu of taxes, and congressional action, file of items numbered 53-5i on financing of housing projects, statement on payments in lieu of taxes prepared by L. Bloomberg for William Wheaton, 1948 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres., statements, memoranda on presentation of data, telegram on eligibility for occupancy, letter of congratulations from Lewis Mumford, request from Nathan Straus to write a chapter in his book on housing, 1949 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres. concerning personal matters, including honorary degree for Ernest Bohn (hypothetical development program for Alexandria, Va.), 1950 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Correspondence with local housing authorities and concerning Vinton's speech at May meeting of NAHO; 2 photographs of blackboard on which policy on finance developed for Public Housing Administration, 1951 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres., to local housing authoritites and for testimonial dinner; memorandum (unsigned) on inclusion of low rent project in Norfolk, Va. in redevelopment project, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres. on staff and personal matters, announcement of appointment of Administrator Cole, memoranda from cole and to Commissioner Slusser by Vinton Transmitting report "Improving the Usefulness and Acceptability of Low-Rent Housing Program" based on suggestions of Vinton and staff, 1953 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Correspondence on staff matters, 1954 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Correspondence on staff and retirement matters, with D.K. Pfeffer of First National City Bank of New York on rates on PHA notes, clippings and statement on attack by National Association of Real Estate Boards, 1955 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres. concerning staff, material for book, magazine article, introduction for Charles Abrams, article and statistics on public housing for Stevenson-Kefauver campaign committee, outline of statutes under which PHA operates, 1956 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Reports (Chron.)-Corres., especially concerning Vinton's resignation from the PHA, Aug. 2, 1957; memoranda on rejuvenation of Public Housing Program and proposed legislation, announcement of Vinton's election to Board of Directors of National Housing Conference (Box 20)
- Series VII. Subject Arrangement, 1941-1956
  - Variety of single items under headings: National Lawyers Guild, National Committee on Social Legislation, report on Post War Low-Rent Public Housing Program; "Greenbelt Plan" for community redevelopment; "Appropriations" for Public War Housing 1944; "Finance and Accounts" 1944; charts for General Housing Act of 1945 (MS), 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1945-1949 (by Subj.)-Corres., statements, memorandum (single items) under headings; Carl Chatter, American Municipal Assoc. 1948-9; "Council of State Governments" 1948; "Regional Economists" 1948 (duplicates); "Legislation, Housing (Misc.) 1946;" David "Krooth" General Counsel on his resignation, 1946; "Income-Family" 1948; "Local Housing Authorities" draft on PHA-LHA relationships 1948, Housing Legislation Information Service report on meeting, Nov. 10, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1950-1953 (by Subj.)-Correspondence, statements, reports (single items): "Reorganization Housing," "Housing Standards and Designs" on comparision PHA-FHA standards 1950; "Surveys and studies of Housing Conditions" 1951; "NAHO-General" questionnaire on relationship HHFA employees and NAHO 1952; "Urban Redevelopment" 1952; "Va. (Norfolk)" land tranfer 1952; "bond Buyer" 1953; "NAHO Fiscal Policy Committee" 1953; "SCUR" [slum clearance and urban redevelopment] proposal to consolidate Title I and Title II in one Administrative Agency 1953; "Site Acquistions" for Winston Salem, N.C. and Milwaukee, Wisc. 1953, clippings from Congressional Record retirement Raymond Foley "HHFA Administrator, March 18, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1954-1956 (by Subj.)-Correspondence, statements, reports (single items) under headings: "Ohio, Cleveland" 1954; "Legis. Housing-1954;" "Delegations of Authority" from HHFA Manual 1954; "Hoover commission [x "Capital Grants']" statement of reasons for use of Annual Contributions instead of capital grants to assist public housing 1955; "Housing Amendments 1956;" "Training [x Warren Jay Vinton Speeches, Articles etc.-1956];" "History of housing" in lecture by Carter McFarland at HHFA Training Conference 1956 (Box 1)
  - Misc. corres., statistics, charts, announcement of meetings, report on USHA program, MS notes "The Physical Plant of the American People" (Box 27)
  - Study of Population Redistribution-Correspondence with Carter Goodrich, Study of Population Redistribution, Washington, D.C., concerning article Vinton while studying at Columbia was to do on classifying states according to when frontier ended, June 19-27, 1934 (Box 23)
  - Fifty thousand rehoused families, An Analysis of the Low-Rent Housing Program Based on the Records of One Hundred and Sixty Three Projects, Nov. 1942. Typescript 316 pp. incl. tables (Box 20)
- Series VIII. Housing Legislation-Files Arranged by year then alphabetically by folder title
  - Wagner Ellenbogen Bill, 1936
    - "Congressional History-1936 WEB"-Congressional Record clipping on Bill 4424, Wagener Ellenbogen Bill, in Senate and House of Representatives, April 3-June 19, 1936 (Box 6)
    - "Drafts of Bill-1936 WEB"-TS copy Wagner Bill with proposed changes, Committee prints of Wagner bill in Senate, March 23, 31, 1936; Bill S. 4424, Feb. 24, 1936; Bill S. 4424, June 17,1936; Bill HR 12164, April 3, 1936, March 20-June 17, 1936 (Box 6)
    - "Hearing-Senate Committee-1936 WEB"-Statements and testimony before Senate and Senate Committee on Education and Labour by Harold Ickes, Frances Perkins, Senator R. Wager, William Green, president of AFL and others, MC, April 20-23, 1936 (Box 6)
    - "Miscellaneous-1936 WEB"-Speech by Robert Wagner, statement by Henry Ellenbogen, National Public Housing Conference flyer, FHA statement, analysis, Jan. 30-May 5, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Notes and Suggestions-1936 (WEB) [Wagner Ellenbogen Bill]-MS notes and memoranda, recommendations from NAHO meeting of March 23, 1936; Mss. minutes of meeting, March 25, 1936, proposed amendments, some correspondence, reports comments by Labor Housing Conference, by Coleman Woodbury, Don Price of Central Housing Committee, March 16-Dec. 2, 1936 (Box 6)